Finding Aid for Clifford Keen Papers 1925-1985
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Clifford Keen Papers 1925-1985
Keen, Clifford, 1901-
1 linear ft. and 2 oversize volumes
University of Michigan wrestling coach. Correspondence, wrestling meet rosters and rules, scrapbooks and clippings, biographical and personal material, and photographs.
861038 AC Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was received from Mr. Keen in November 1985. Donor no. 7257
The collection is open for research.
Clifford Keen was born in 1901 on a ranch in Western Oklahoma. He attended Oklahoma A & M (now known as Oklahoma State University) and was a star in football, track, and wrestling. He received All-American mention in football, sprinted in track, and was undefeated for three years as a wrestler. He was selected for the 1924 U.S. Olympic team, but did not compete because of a broken rib.
Keen became head wrestling coach at the University of Michigan in 1925. During the next 45 years he produced 13 Big Ten championship teams and 3 second place squads. His wrestlers won 11 individual national crowns and 81 Big Ten titles. He compiled a dual meet record of 268-91-9.
Keen served as a naval commander during World War II, after which he returned to Michigan to continue coaching. His 45-year tenure at the University of Michigan is one of the longest in collegiate coaching annals.
Keen served on the U.S. Olympic Committee from 1938 to 1952, and was manager of the U.S. team for the 1948 Olympic Games. He pioneered the development of safety equipment and head-gear for wrestlers, and started an athletic equipment company to which he has devoted much time since retiring from coaching in 1970. He has received numerous honors and awards, and was inducted into the National Wrestling Hall of Fame in Stillwater, Oklahoma in September, 1976.
The Clifford Keen collection, consisting of 1 linear foot and 2 outsize volumes, is divided into 6 series: Biographical material, Correspondence, Wrestling Meet Rules and Rosters, Newspaper clippings, Business and Professional Activities, and Photographs.
Of special interest are 15 correspondence folders containing letters written primarily in the 1920s and 1930s. These are arranged alphabetically by individual and/or institution. Nearly all correspondence between universities is classified by the name of the institution. Some of the material, dated 1925, was written before Keen's move to the University of Michigan. Although not addressed to or written by Keen, these letters are included in the first correspondence folder. The last folder contains letters, 1971-1977, written and received after Keen's retirement. The collection includes two oversize scrapbooks which are of particular interest in that they contain newspaper clippings and photographs documenting Keen's activities from 1926 to 1955 and from 1955 to 1978. The volumes are arranged by wrestling season and include newpaper accounts of wrestling meets, feature stories on Keen and individual wrestlers, and team and individual photos.
Subjects:
Keen, Clifford, 1901-; University of Michigan. Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Wrestling.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Keen, Clifford, 1901-; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Football.; Wrestling.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Biographical
  - Awards and Honors (Box 1)
  - Wrestling Meet Programs, 1965, 1969, 1970 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - 1925 (Box 1)
  - 1930-1936, 15 folders (Box 1)
    (arranged alphabetically)
  - 1971-1977 (Box 1)
- Wrestling Meet Rosters And Rules
  - 1924-1927, 1934, 1940, 1963 (Box 1)
- Clippings and Scrapbooks
  - Clippings
    - Personal, mostly, undated (Box 1)
    - Personal, 1980s (Box 1)
    - Team achievements, mostly, undated (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1926-1955 (Volume 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1956-1978 (Volume 2)
- Business and Professional Activities
  - Cliff Keen Athletic Company (catalogues), 1985 (Box 1)
  - Championship Wrestling, 1973 (Box 1)
    (manual co-authored by Clifford Keen, Charles Speidel, and Ramond Swartz)
- Photographs, 1926-1978
  - Portraits (Box 1)
  - Clifford Keen with teams, individual athletes, and non-athletic groups (Box 1)
  - Groups and individual athletes, identified (Box 1)
  - Wrestling Team Photos, 1926-1931, 1933-1945, 1950-1953, 1955-1957 (Box 1)
    (Mostly Rentschler Studio prints removed from Vol. 1 of the Keen scrapbooks. Team Photos for 1946-1947 could not be removed from the scrapbook.)
  - 150 pound football team, 1947 (Box 1)
    (Includes assistant coach George Allen)